Inventory of the Pavel Źáček collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Pavel Źáček collection
1948-2001
2000C73
Źáček, Pavel, collector
36 manuscript boxes (14.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Case files, reports, and diaries and interrogation transcripts of Czech senior secret police personnel, relating to secret service activities in Czechoslovakia. Includes a summary of the secret police file on Václav Havel. Photocopies of originals in the Národní archiv.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection may not be copied until 2056 April 10.
Collection is otherwise open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Searchworks at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Národní archiv.
Biographical Note
Born in 1969, Źáček earned his PhD in mass communication at Charles University, Prague in 2001. His dissertation topic was the illegal magazine "V Boj." From 1993 to 1997 he served as head of the Documentation Section, Office for the Documentation and Investigation of the Activities of the State Security Service/Crimes of Communism, and was editor of the anthology Securitas Imperii, a periodical concerned with state security documents and studies, from 1994 to 1999. In 1997 he became head of the team for the documentation of the role of Czechoslovak officials in Korea and Vietnam, in cooperation with the U.S. Office of the Assistant Secretary of Defense for POW/Missing Personnel Affairs. In 1998 he was appointed deputy director, Office for the Documentation and Investigation of the Crimes of Communism, and then served as senior researcher at the Institute of Contemporary History, Academy of Sciences in Prague from 1999 to 2006. After a short period as acting director of the Security Services Archive from 2007 to 2008, Źáček was appointed director of the Institute for the Study of Totalitarian Regimes in January 2008. He was a visiting scholar at the Hoover Archives Summer Workshop on Soviet Communism in July 2009.
Scope and Content of Collection
Case files, reports, diaries, and interrogation transcripts of Czech senior secret police personnel, relating to secret service activities in Czechoslovakia. Includes a summary of the secret police file on Václav Havel. Contains personnel files on State Security agents, orders and plans, and reports from Ministry of Security X and II Directorates. Photocopies of originals in the Státní ústřední in Prague.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Secret service--Czechoslovakia.; Civil rights--Czechoslovakia.; Havel, Václav.
Collection Contents
- Subject file, 1965-2000 (Box 1)
  Includes articles by Pavel Źáček, interrogation transcripts, and diaries of former security agents and Ministry of Interior notes
  - "Státní Bezpecnost Kontra Václav Havel (1965-1968)," by Pavel Źáček, 1994 (Folder 1: 1)
    Includes summary of Vaclav Havel's secret police file
  - Articles on Státni Bezpečnost (StB) former agents, and other related articles, by Pavel Źáček, 1992-2000 (Folder 1: 2-3)
  - "Vzestupy a pády Bohumíra Molnára. Kariéra generála Státní bezpečnosti," article by Pavel Źáček,. ("Rise and Fall of Bohumír Molnér. The Carrier of the General of State Security."), 1992-2000 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Interrogations of former StB agents, 1990-1991 (Folder 1)
    - Lt. Gen. Alojz Lorenc, First Deputy Minister of Interior, Prague, 1990 December 10 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Maj. Dr. Petr Zak, Chief of 10th Department Second Main Administration State Security, Prague, 1991 February 13 (Folder 1: 6)
    - Ing. František Kincl, Minister of Interior, Prague, 1990 December 28 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Ministry of Interior, notes about 1989 demonstration in Prague (Folder 1: 8)
  - Copies of diaries by former StB leaders, 1989-1990 (Folder 1)
    - Deputy Minister of Interior, Lt. Col. O. Sedlak, 1989 November 10 - December 20 (Folder 1: 9)
    - Maj. Dr. Miroslav Chovanec, Deputy Chief of Second Main Administration of State Security, 1989 September 2 - 1990 January 2 (Folder 1: 10)
    - Lt. Col. DR. Karel Vykypěl, Chief of Second Main Administration of State Security, 1989 November 27 - 1990 April 28 (Folder 1: 11)
  - "Nástroj Triedneho Štátu. Organizácia Ministerstiev Vnitra a Bezpečnostných Zborov 1953-1990," edited by Pavel Źáček, 2005 (Box 1)
    (The organization of the Ministries of Interior and the Security Forces)
  - Organization of the Ministry of Interior of Czechoslovakia (MV), 2005 (Box 1)
    - 1953-1968 (Folder 1: 12)
    - 1969-1989 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Organization of Territorial Departments of the Ministry of Interior and National Security Corps (SNB), 1953-1990 (Folder 1: 14-15)
- Karta Prislusnika-Úřad pro Dokumentaci a Vyšetřováni (KP-UDV) Files, 1951-1989 (Box 2-17)
  Contains personnel files and registration cards of agents, from the Office for Documentation and Investigation. Most files are in an unidentified numerical order
  - KP-UDV-000001-105000 (Folder 2: 1-9)
  - KP-UDV-105001-115000 (Folder 3: 1-9)
  - KP-UDV-105001-115000 (Folder 4: 1-2)
  - KP-UDV-115001-135000 (Folder 4: 3-9)
  - KP-UDV-115001-135000 (Folder 5: 1-4)
  - KP-UDV-135001-141000 (Folder 5: 5-8)
  - KP-UDV-141001-142000 (Folder 6: 1-10)
  - KP-UDV-142001-144000 (Folder 7: 1-6)
  - KP-UDV-144001-150000 (Folder 8: 1-10)
  - KP-UDV-150001-158000 (Folder 9: 1)
  - KP-UDV-158001-162000 (Folder 9: 2-10)
  - KP-UDV-162001-170000 (Folder 10: 1-11)
  - KP-UDV-170001-180000 (Folder 11: 1-10)
  - KP-UDV-180001-190000 (Folder 12: 1)
  - KP-UDV-190001-210000 (Folder 12: 2-4)
  - KP-UDV-210001-230000 (Folder 12: 5-7)
  - KP-UDV-230001-790000 (Folder 12: 8-10)
  - KP-UDV-230001-790000 (Folder 13: 1)
  - KP-UDV-790001-916000 (Folder 13: 2-8)
  - KP-UDV-790001-916000 (Folder 14: 1-7)
  - Nové-KP (New personnel registration cards) 1-2, 1970-1994 (Folder 14: 8-9)
  - Nové-KP (New personnel registration cards) 3-12, 1970-1994 (Folder 15: 1-10)
  - Annex to personnel files, 1970-1991 (Folder 15: 11)
  - Nové-KP, 1970-1991 (Folder 16: 1-5)
  - Seznam KP (List of personnel files, alphabetical), 1970s (Folder 16-17)
    - Part 1, 1-3 (Folder 16: 6-8)
    - Part 2, 1 (Folder 16: 9)
    - Part 2, 2-3 (Folder 17: 1-2)
  - Personnel characteristics and qualifications for the potential position as Chief of Public Security (Folder 17: 3)
- Orders (Rozkazy) Files, 1951-1989 (Box 17-19)
  Includes secret orders and guidelines from the Minister of Interior and Chiefs of State Security Divisions, related to national security issues, also Ministry of Interior bulletins (Věstníky). Also includes a list of "back-up" agents
  - Rozkazy, 1956-1989 (Folder 17: 4-9)
  - Rozkazy, 1956-1989 (contd.) (Folder 18: 1-11)
  - Věstníky (bulletins), 1956-1989 (Folder 18-19:)
    - 1969 (Folder 18: 12)
    - 1970-1971 (Folder 18: 13)
    - 1972 (Folder 19: 1)
    - 1973 (Folder 19: 2)
    - 1974-1975 (Folder 19: 3)
    - 1976-1978 (Folder 19: 4)
    - 1979 (Folder 19: 5)
    - 1981-1982 (Folder 19: 6)
    - 1983 (Folder 19: 7)
    - 1984-1986 (Folder 19: 8)
    - 1987 (Folder 19: 9)
    - 1988-1989 (Folder 19: 10)
  - Metodické pokyny (Guidelines), Naŕízení (Regulations), 1960-1982 (Folder 19: 11)
- X-Správa Zbor Národní Bezpečnosti (ZNB) (Tenth Directorate of the National Security Council) files, 1984-1988 (Box 19-24)
  Contains analysis, statistics, reports, and guidelines about security issues, work plan evaluations (vyhodnocení plánu práce), reviews (informace), statements (vykazy), from various divisions
  - Vyhodnocení (work plan evaluations) (Folder 19-20)
    - Bratislava - XII Administration, 1984-1988 (Folder 19-20)
      - 1984 (Folder 19: 12)
      - 1985 (Folder 19: 13)
      - 1986 (Folder 19: 14)
      - 1987 (Folder 20: 1)
      - 1988 (Folder 20: 2)
    - Košice, Department #2 (KE-II-Odb), 1984-1988 (Folder 20)
      - 1984 (Folder 20: 3)
      - 1985 (Folder 20: 4)
      - 1986 (Folder 20: 5)
      - 1987 (Folder 20: 6)
      - 1988 (Folder 20: 7)
    - Slovak Republic State Security SStB.SR (Bratislava, Banská Bystrica, Košice), 1988 (Folder 20: 8-9)
    - Czech Republic State Security SStB.ČR (Praha, Plzeň, Brno, Ostrava, České Budějovice, Hr. Králové), 1988 (Folder 20: 10-11)
    - Banská Bystrica, Department #2 (BB-II-Odb), 1984-1987 (Folder 21)
      - 1984 (Folder 21: 1-3)
      - 1985 (Folder 21: 2)
      - 1987 (Folder 21: 3)
    - Košice, Department #2, 1986 (Folder 21: 4)
    - Bratislava, Department #2 (BA-II-Odb), 1984-1987 (Folder 21)
      - 1984 (Folder 21: 5)
      - 1985 (Folder 21: 6)
      - 1986 (Folder 21: 7)
      - 1987 (Folder 21: 8)
  - Plány (annual work plans), 1985-1988 (Folder 21-22)
    - Bratislava - XII Administration, 1985-1986 (Folder 21)
      - 1985 (Folder 21: 9)
      - 1986 (Folder 21: 10)
    - Bratislava, Department #2, 1988 (Folder 21: 11)
    - Košice, Department #2 (KE-II-Odb), 1985-1987 (Folder 21-22)
      - 1985 (Folder 21: 12)
      - 1986 (Folder 22: 1)
      - 1987 (Folder 22: 2)
    - České Budějovice, Department #2 (CB-II-Odb), 1988 (Folder 22: 3)
    - Banská Bystrica, Department #2 (BB-II-Odb), 1985-1988 (Folder 22: 3)
      - 1985 (Folder 22: 4)
      - 1986 (Folder 22: 5)
      - 1987 (Folder 22: 6)
      - 1988 (Folder 22: 7)
    - Bratislava, Department #2, 1985-1987 (Folder 22)
      - 1985 (Folder 22: 8)
      - 1986 (Folder 22: 9)
      - 1987 (Folder 22: 10)
    - Bratislava - XII Administration, 1987-1988 (Folder 22)
      - 1987 (Folder 22: 11)
      - 1988 (Folder 22: 12)
  - Plány. FMV Provadeci plany (Federal Ministry of Interior work plans), 1978-1988 (Folder 23)
    - 1978 (Folder 23: 1)
    - 1979 (Folder 23: 2)
    - 1980 (Folder 23: 3)
    - 1981 (Folder 23: 4)
    - 1982 (Folder 23: 5)
    - 1983 (Folder 23: 6)
    - 1984 (Folder 23: 7)
    - 1985 (Folder 23: 8)
    - 1986 (Folder 23: 9)
    - 1987 (Folder 23: 10)
    - 1988 (Folder 23: 11)
  - Plány, 1985-1987 (Folder 23)
    - Department #4 (10-4-odb), 1987 (Folder 23: 12)
    - Department #5 (10-5-odb), 1985; 1987 (Folder 23: 12)
  - Ctvrtletni Informace (Quarterly Reviews), 1984-1987 (Folder 23)
    - Department #4, 1984; 1987 (Folder 23: 13)
    - Department #5, 1987 (Folder 23: 13)
    - General, 1987 (Folder 23: 13)
  - Vyhodnocení (work plan evaluations), 1984-1987 (Folder 23: 14)
    - Department #3, 1987
    - Department #4, 1984-1987
    - Department #5, 1987
  - Plány,Department #3, 1985-1987 (Folder 24: 1)
  - Informace, Department #3, 1987 (Folder 24: 1)
  - Vyhodnocení, 1985-1987 (Folder 24)
    - Department #2 (Folder 24)
      - 1985 (Folder 24: 2)
      - 1986 (Folder 24: 3)
      - 1987 (Folder 24: 4)
  - Plány, Department #2, 1985-1987 (Folder 24: 5)
  - Vykazy (Statements), 1986-1987 (Folder 24: 5)
  - Informace, Department #4, 1984-1986 (Folder 24: 6)
  - Vyhodnocení, 1984-1986 (Folder 24)
    - Department #1, 1984-1987 (Folder 24)
      - 1984-1986 (Folder 24: 7)
      - 1987 (Folder 24: 8)
  - Plány, 1985-1984 (Folder 24: 8)
    - Department #1, 1985; 1987 (Folder 24: 8)
  - Informace, 1985-1987 (Folder 24: 9)
    - Department #1, 1985-1987 (Folder 24: 9)
  - Vykazy (Statements of Preventative Measures), 1984-1987 (Folder 24: 10)
- II-Správa Sbor Národní Bezpečnosti (SNB) (Second Directorate of the National Security Council) files, 1988-1989 (Box 25)
  Contains work plan evaluations (vyhodnocení plánu práce), reviews (informace), statements (vykazy), from various divisions, includes notes about discharging the Státní bezpečnost (StB) officers and lists of names
  - Vyhodnocení, 1988-1989 (Folder 25)
    - Department #9, 1988-1989 (Folder 25: 1)
    - Department #10, 1988-1989 (Folder 25: 2)
    - Department #11, 1988-1989 (Folder 25: 3)
    - Department #12, 1988-1989 (Folder 25: 4)
  - Informace, 1989 (Folder 25)
    - Department #12, 1989 (Folder 25: 4)
  - Vykazy, 1988, Department #10 (Folder 25: 5)
  - List of names of StB officers, 1970s and 1980s (Folder 25: 6-9)
- Státní bezpečnost (StB) (State Security) agents files, 1970s and 1980s (Box 26-36)
  Includes lists of names and detailed characteristics of StB agents, personal and professional CV files, questionnaires, evaluations, certificates, copies of photographs of agents and defectors. Arranged in two groups, alphabetical or by file number
  - By file number, 1970s-1980s (Folder 26-27)
    - 13 6052 (Folder 26: 1)
    - 13 7229 (Folder 26: 2)
    - 14 1361 (Folder 26: 3)
    - 14 1394 (Folder 26: 4)
    - 14 1573 (Folder 26: 5)
    - 16 4023-16 0452 (Folder 26: 6)
    - 16 4026 (Folder 26: 7)
    - 16 4304 (Folder 26: 8)
    - 16 4539-16 4792 (Folder 26: 9)
    - 16 4982 (Folder 26: 10)
    - 16 4801 (Folder 26: 11)
    - 16 4929 (Folder 26: 12)
    - 16 6033 (Folder 26: 13)
    - 17 0146 (Folder 26: 14)
    - 17 2151 (Folder 26: 15)
    - 17 2321 (Folder 26: 16)
    - 17 6697-18 7773 (Folder 27: 1)
    - 18 8373 (Folder 27: 2)
    - 19 5047 (Folder 27: 3)
    - 20 7587 (Folder 27: 4)
    - 22 4942 (Folder 27: 5)
    - 22 6097 (Folder 27: 6)
    - 23 0670 (Folder 27: 7)
  - By name, 1970s-1980s (Folder 27-36)
    - Andrejsek, Jaromir (Folder 27: 8)
    - Arazim, Ludvík (Folder 27: 9-10)
    - Arazim, Ludvík (Folder 28: 1)
    - Bohůnek, Miloslav (Folder 28: 2)
    - Černý, Otakar (Folder 28: 3)
    - Defektori (photos of defectors) (Folder 28: 4)
    - Dvorský, Vladimí Fiala (Folder 28: 5)
    - Foto StB (photos of State Security agents) (Folder 28: 6)
    - Franta, Josef (Folder 28: 7)
    - Had, Alois (Folder 28: 8)
    - Havlíček, Václav (Folder 29: 1)
    - Hladík, Miloš (Folder 29: 2)
    - Hrabik, Jaroslav (Folder 29: 3)
    - Hrbáček, Jaroslav (Folder 29: 4-6)
    - Ježek, Jiří (Folder 29: 7)
    - Ježek, Jiří (Folder 30: 1)
    - Kavan, Antonín (Folder 30: 2-4)
    - Klíma, Jaroslav (Folder 30: 5-9)
    - Koníček, Ivan (Folder 31: 1-2)
    - Kováč, Jén (Folder 31: 3-4)
    - Kožuch, Albín (Folder 31: 5-7)
    - Kraus, Zdenĕk (Folder 31: 8)
    - Kubr, Jaroslav (Folder 31: 9-10)
    - Kubr, Jaroslav (Folder 32: 1-2)
    - Kucian, Miloš (Folder 32: 3-4)
    - Ludvík, Josef (Folder 32: 5-8)
    - Mareček, Vladimír (Folder 32: 9-10)
    - Mareš, Josef (Folder 32: 11-12)
    - Miller, Jaroslav (Folder 32: 13)
    - Miřijovský, Vladimír (Folder 33: 1-2)
    - Nacvalač, Miloslav (Folder 33: 3)
    - Řepík, Vladislav (Folder 33: 4)
    - Řezníček, Ladislav (Folder 33: 5-6)
    - Říha, Václav (Folder 33: 7-9)
    - Růžička, Josef (Folder 33: 10)
    - Ruzne (various names) (Folder 34: 1-2)
    - Rybín, Jiří (Folder 34: 3)
    - Rychtařik, Zdenek (Folder 34: 4-6)
    - Šeda (Folder 34: 7)
    - Šefrna, Lubomír (Folder 34: 8)
    - Šíma, Václav (Folder 34: 9-11)
    - Soudný, Jiří (Folder 35: 1-2)
    - Stárek, Vladimír (Folder 35: 3-4)
    - Šulc, František (Folder 35: 5-9)
    - Tomisek (Folder 36: 1)
    - Tůma, Miloslav (Folder 36: 2)
    - Vach, František (Folder 36: 3-4)
    - Other names (Folder 36: 5-8)